SIMRAN ARORA

Philadelphia, PA

CONTACT | 770 624 4256

WEBSITE | Simran Arora's Website

LINKEDIN | Simran Arora

EMAIL | arorasim@upenn.edu

Master of City Planning candidate with three years of professional experience in urban design, planning and project management. Recent internship experience in demographic, economic & real estate analysis and geospatial data development. Interested in application of data science and urban technologies for building safer and liveable cities, and looking for opportunities in the transportation planning, economic development and urban analytics industries.

EDUCATION

University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia PA, Expected May 2023

Master of City Planning, Concentration in Transportation and Infrastructure Planning

- Leadership: Councilwoman on Inter-Professional Women's Committee, Leadership for Penn Transportation Club
- Relevant Projects: Comparing Factors for Bike Trip Generation for Philly & Boston, Visualizing Philly's Crash Data, Planning Studio for West Philadelphia's Neighborhoods, Grey's Ferry Neighborhood Profile, Predicting Home Sale Prices for Philadelphia, Exploring NDVI in Philadelphia

Academy of Architecture, University of Mumbai, Mumbai India, May 2018

Bachelor of Architecture

- Awards: PCERF Urban Design category winner (2018), Scholarchs Urban Design category winner (2018),
 Destech Challenge for Smart Cities (2nd Place + special mention), Writing Architecture (2015), Ruebens
 Trophy for Academic Excellence (2015), Louis I Kahn Documentation Trophy (2015)
- Leadership: Class representative (1st and 4th year), Cultural representative (2nd and 3rd year), Teaching Assistant for the 1st year orientation program, Researcher for <u>Windows to Vernacular</u>

RELEVANT EXPERIENCE

U3 Advisors, Philadelphia PA, May 2022 - current

Graduate Intern

- Demographic, Economic & Real Estate Analysis: Analyzed census, employment, migration and real estate
 data using R to build insights for downtown development. Organized data spatially using ArcGIS to build
 reports using maps and data visualization graphics.
- **Retail Demand Forecasting:** Developed models based on ESRI Business Analyst reports for supportable retail square footage for a university town and a downtown neighborhood.

PolicyMap, Philadelphia PA, May 2022 - August 2022, *3 months* **Data Development Intern**

- Data Development: Cleaned, processed and documented data in SQL and created pipelines for new datasets.
- Updating Datasets: Weekly & monthly data processing for the PolicyMap website for healthcare, housing
 and census-related datasets. Collaborated with production team to update data on the platform.

StudioPOD, Mumbai India, May 2018 - July 2021, *3 years* **Architect**

- Mixed Use Masterplanning: Led a 100 acre residential, low-density masterplanning project in Bangalore, India. Developed a detailed masterplan, comprehensive planning report and several concept presentations. Assisted in two ~70 acre mixed-used masterplans based on the concept of landscape urbanism. Designed a concept report, renderings and street designs.
- University Masterplanning: Worked on a ~150 acre university campus masterplan for alternative educations systems. Created designs based on modular architecture and human-scale, with traditional+local design techniques.

- Urban Design and Placemaking: Assisted in a heritage precinct masterplanning project and created street designs based on heavy pedestrian traffic, geared towards planning for large traditional festivals and markets.
- **Concept Proposals:** Worked on a range of diverse proposals for multimodal transportation strategies, urban placemaking through art, residential masterplans and commercial landscape projects.

Eyes on the Canal, Chennai India, August 2018 - May 2019, 9 months Part-time Urban Design Consultant

- Advisory: Won the 'Eyes on the Canal' competition organized by GIZ and UDC, India, as part of a 5-person team to develop strategies based on participatory planning and placemaking to revive the Buckingham Canal in Chennai, India. The funding continued for a year to develop a comprehensive report for several urban local bodies in Chennai.
- **Community Engagement:** Developed several presentations and outreach materials for community meetings. Collaborated with two other teams to create a final report for the City.
- **Biennales:** This work has been presented at the London Design Biennale 2021 (India Pavilion) and International Architecture Biennale Rotterdam (TBD).

World Resources Institute, Mumbai India, December 2017 - Jan 2018, 2 months Intern

 Assisted in the 'Cities Safer by Design' initiative. Developed a proposal to create continuous pedestrian networks in the Island City of Mumbai as part of a city-level de-congestion plan.

Green Space Alliance, Mumbai India, November 2016 - March 2017, 5 months Landscape Architecture Intern

- **Public Realm Design:** Designed a plaza and public realm in a commercial district in Bangalore, India. Created visualizations and graphics for spaces, as well as conceptual sketches for sculptures.
- Mixed-Use Development: Assisted in creating neighborhood parks and gardens programmed for residential townships in Mumbai and Thane. Assisted in a 50 acres landscape masterplan for a mixed-use township in Gujarat, India.

RESEARCH + TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Partners for Urban Knowledge, Action & Research, Mumbai India, June 2018 - June 2019, 1 year Youth Fellowship Recipient (Part-Time Researcher)

- **Urban Research:** Led a team of 8 Fellows to develop designs for spaces under flyovers. Studied negative spaces under flyovers in Mumbai, created and conducted surveys and interviews with surrounding communities to propose a design for an identified urban void. All the work was compiled into a report: 'Studying Urban Voids'. This work was presented at the Tata Institute of Social Sciences in June 2019.
- **Workshops:** Attended workshops and panels on various social sciences topics. Conducted a workshop on community mapping and data visualization.

Academy of Architecture, Rachana Sansad, Mumbai India, August 2018 - November 2018, 4 months Visiting Researcher

 Assisted in the development of a project to document cultural representations and elements in Mumbai's communities. Created 'Project 999' - visually documenting ~1000 residential doors in Mumbai.

SKILLS

Transportation Planning R (STPLANR) | VISUM & VISSIM

Geospatial Analysis ArcGIS | Python | R | SQL | JavaScript | ESRI Business Analyst & Field Maps

Design Software AutoCAD | SketchUp | Adobe Suite (InDesign, Photoshop, Illustrator) | Rhino | Lumion

Urban Design | Street Design | Plaza + Public Parks | Waterfront Design | Design Programming

Other Writing | Graphic Design